<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Act against conventicles executed with a vindication of the Bedford-shire justices proceedings from the aspersions of a false, impertinent and libellous pamphlet entituled, A true and impartial narrative of some illegal and arbitrary proceedings by certain justices of the peace and others, against several innocent and peaceable non-conformints in and near the town of Bedford, upon pretence of putting in execution the late act against conventicles.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16652</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8435457</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204258</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264211036</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing A446</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08435457</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204258)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1245:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Act against conventicles executed with a vindication of the Bedford-shire justices proceedings from the aspersions of a false, impertinent and libellous pamphlet entituled, A true and impartial narrative of some illegal and arbitrary proceedings by certain justices of the peace and others, against several innocent and peaceable non-conformints in and near the town of Bedford, upon pretence of putting in execution the late act against conventicles.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.G.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Bunyan, John, 1628-1688. --  True and impartial narrative of some illegal and arbitrary proceedings by certain justices of the peace and others.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Conventicle act (1670)</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Bedford.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204258:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204258:2"/>
            <p>THE ACT AGAINST Conventicles EXECUTED: WITH A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Bedford-shire</hi> JUSTICES Proceedings, <hi>From the Aspersions of a</hi> False, Impertinent, and Libellous <hi>PAMPHLET,</hi> Entituled, A true and impartial <hi>NARRATIVE</hi> of some Illegal and Arbritrary <hi>Proceedings</hi> by certain <hi>Justices of the Peace,</hi> and others, against several Innocent and Peaceable <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> in and near the Town of <hi>Bedford,</hi> upon pretence of putting in Execution the late ACT against <hi>Conventicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> M. DC. LXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="authors_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:204258:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204258:3"/>
            <head>The ACT against CONVENTICLES EXECUTED: <hi>With</hi> A <hi>VINDICATION</hi> of the <hi>Bedfordshire</hi> JUSTICES Proceedings, from the Asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of a false, impertinent, and libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous PAMPHLET, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I was informed, That the Justices (generally) did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it too great a lessening both of themselves and their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (which they will justifie to the World) to take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of so wretched a Scrowl, void both of sense and integrity; upon examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Paper, I did believe it very unfit, that such a bundle of scandalous Falshoods, should
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204258:4"/> have free access to all sorts of Readers without any contradiction: Which is all the account why I took upon me the trouble to give it an Answer▪ And yet, notwithstanding this condiscention, I have so good an opinion of my self, as to think that this sordid Scribler can no ways deserve to be acquainted with my name, and therefore I shall chuse (by concealing that) to pelt him in the dark, according to his own Law at Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, before I make the first Onslaught upon the Ribaldry of this Paper, I must prevail some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon the patience of the Reader, by engaging to be as brief as it is possible upon such a subject: Very well knowing, That both the Names and Actions of all such latent Traducers, are then only placed in their proper Sphere, when they are rank'd in a Gaolers Calendar before the Assizes. And this in the first place will be evident enough, upon an impartial Examination of the Title Page of this Libel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where you shall find, the</hi> due Execution of an Act of Parliament, <hi>styled</hi> Illegal and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Proceedings, <hi>by the same Antiphrasis (which in our Idiom is coursely translated a plain
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204258:4"/> Lye) as</hi> disobedient and turbulent Offenders, <hi>are called</hi> innocent and peaceable Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists. <hi>Therefore whoever will become a competent Interpreter of this new Text, must</hi> Janus-<hi>like have two fronts, one with Eyes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to read Pretences, but those of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing must be placed behind, to inable him to discover the Antartick Truth. And the same Rules also, notwithstanding their pretences to sincerity and innocence, are applicable both to their Actions and Dealings as well as their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: To say nothing of their false Weights and Measures, for which they have been often convicted; of the Arraignment of several of them at the Bar, for wickedly seducing a Servant to steal his Masters Goods, their clandestine Traffick and Compacts for the same Commodities; of the impudence of a Teacher, who undertook to Dispence</hi> his Gifts <hi>to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a stolen Cloak; their Complaints of one another in the Commissaries Court of brutish Incontinence: And to complete their Morals amongst us, they justifie their Alliegeance by Acts of Rebellion, and pay Reverence to Magistrates, by traducing Superiours,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204258:5"/> and make Narratives of the</hi> Truth, <hi>by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> Falshoods; <hi>as if they had been taught in</hi> Scoggens <hi>School to untile Houses, to find Hares, or more properly, in their own phrase, to ride to</hi> Jerusalem <hi>with their faces mounted to the Beasts posteriors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which will be apparent enough, by unrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the</hi> Letter, <hi>the Vizard-Mask to the</hi> Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative; <hi>in which since he hath made bold to put the Justices Names to the Character of the</hi> Non-conformists, <hi>the best way of answering, will be by changing its part, and stating it a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selyte, and then republish it to the World, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Truth after this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some proceedings at</hi> Bedford, <hi>pursuant of the late Act of Parliament</hi> (a true Narrative <hi>whereof is herewith published</hi>) afford won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and dislike <hi>only to those whose Crimes have deserved them; when you have perused this Paper, you will conclude with me and others, that this</hi> Text needs no Comment; <hi>it is plain, that in despight of</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>and in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all</hi> Laws and Rules of Righteousness, Neighbourhood and Humanity, <hi>the</hi> Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists, <hi>resolve once more,</hi> to ruin the Nation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204258:5"/>
               <hi>although the</hi> Instruments (<hi>now as well as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore) are no ways able</hi> to recompence the King and Kingdomes dammage <hi>thereby,</hi> the scandalized <hi>in the Libel are</hi> unconcerned and peaceable; <hi>their immediate</hi> Revilers <hi>are the</hi> scum of the People; <hi>and ought chiefly to be the</hi> appendants (<hi>as in the former sense of this Answer</hi>) of the Commissaries Court: <hi>The most forward</hi> Instrument <hi>of that sort, is one that openly avowed and declared his esteem for</hi> Atheism <hi>above any Religion. If some</hi> Check <hi>be not given to these</hi> extravagancies, <hi>many</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies <hi>will be suddenly</hi> ruined, <hi>the</hi> publick Trade <hi>and</hi> Welfare endangered, <hi>which the</hi> Interest <hi>of some, the</hi> Rage, Revenge <hi>and</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity <hi>of</hi> others <hi>will not admit regard to. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don this trouble, when I have told you the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of this Answer are all true, and will be proved in every part. Thus Excrements become Sanatives, upon some accounts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indeed he is very correspondent to himself, for this Letter is of the same Tenour with the Libel, and both like the Oracles of his grand Patron the Devil, then truest when they are construed back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:204258:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the measure also by which he and his Party, state the Actions of Magistrates; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the composition of some sort of Pictures, on which if you take a direct and right view, they present the pourtraiture of a beautiful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but if side ways with them, their squinting Opticks will shew you a Serpent: The Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration is before you: Now we come to consider the old Trade newly vampt, which he calls a</hi> Narrative, <hi>the first Prologue to above Twenty years Tragedy.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N Lords day, May the fifteenth, &amp;c.] In Nomine Domini</hi> this Wretch begins to insinuate, that an impudent and ignorant Cobler, whom he calls Preacher, might be occasioned from the discourse of a Magistrate, to call the Church of <hi>England Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, &amp;c.</hi> although he afterwards insolently repeated the same words at a publick <hi>Session,</hi> for which he is bound over, at which time all sensible persons (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Comment</hi>) will judge that he would have set a stricter watch upon his tongue, had not his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiling ignorance and malice, and the hopes both of Maintenance, and prevalency from the numbers of his Party, infatuated this <hi>thin-soul'd Wight</hi> at once to discover the common Vogue of them all.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204258:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 4. The only truth in this page is, that <hi>Batti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> hath manifested himself, in the Execution of this Act, to be as honest and dutiful a Subject to the King, in his degree, as any in the Nation; and if when he hired a Chamber to lay up Grain, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller will not allow the <hi>Saints Mault</hi> to be included under that title; it must be by some <hi>quirk of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> for he will find no distinction, either in the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick</hi> or <hi>Philosophy</hi> of ordinary Taunters. By such an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Sophism in the Law, he averrs a fair sale and delivery of the Mault and the Mault-house, although the first Owner at this day continues the possession of both. But one thing more in this case is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent enough (without Annotations) that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the <hi>illegal</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> behaviour of the vulgar people (as it is stated by the <hi>Scribler</hi> himself) yet we hear of no <hi>arbitrary</hi> Outrages committed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of the Act, by the <hi>inhumane</hi> Justices.</p>
            <p>The next complaint is, that (at a dead lift) the Officers did charge some <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the Town to aid and assist them: But setting aside the <hi>Scribes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>Antiphrasis,</hi> they were both ordinary, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Tradesmen: And thus they can dub one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Gentlemen</hi> without Arms, <hi>Saints</hi> without <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, Preachers</hi> without <hi>Orders, Lawyers</hi> without <hi>Learning;</hi> for by the magnifying Glass of the <hi>Spirit</hi> they did ever make their Mole-hills Mountains, and their Geese Swans.</p>
            <p>The next design this <hi>Pamphleter</hi> hath, is to intimate to the World, how much the sufferings of their <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> are against the grain of the people; as if they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204258:7"/> had shut up <hi>Shops</hi> as in a <hi>Pest,</hi> and let the <hi>Shire-Town</hi> dwindle to a Countrey-Village: Here something, like truth, hath unawares dropt from his pen, for it fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out upon a <hi>Holy-day,</hi> the <hi>Conforming</hi> Party had shut up their Shops, and those only were opened, whose <hi>factious Owners</hi> are too well known to be the <hi>Plague</hi> both of Church and State.</p>
            <p>The most remarkable passages in the sixth page are these, first, his <hi>Pharisaical</hi> dubbing a pitiful <hi>Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> into a Dealer in Linnen-Drapery, for indeed they should not be called like other Men.</p>
            <p>And secondly, The <hi>Libellers</hi> own <hi>monstrous</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version into a Distreiner; no other Distress being made in this case, besides what is in the <hi>Libel;</hi> for the Father-in-law of the <hi>Grocer</hi> did immediately lay down his Sons Fine, expressing much indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the actions of him, and sorrow for his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>The last remark in this page, is the <hi>Libellers</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine imitation of those Artists in Filching; who had rather steal, than have any thing given them, to keep their Fingers in ure; so he, to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, but to preserve his faculty bright, hath fathered upon Mr. <hi>F.</hi> a Warrant against a Tanner, which was under the Hands and Seals of all the Justices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 7. Now for the great re-incounter of a silly Widow, seduced from her youth until this day (whose Father indeed was a very honest Gentleman, and detested these Juglers;) but she used her natural Parent then, as she hath since served her heavenly; for being ripe for Conjunction, she stole out of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204258:7"/> house to Marry her self to an ordinary Tradesman, as she now leaves the Church to be espoused to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles; whose Fine was inhansed by her own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discretion to herd her self amongst a pack of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Canary-birds: She bore their burthen at two Meetings, until her Fine amounted to Twenty pounds, for which this spiritual Romancer, by his <hi>Scotch</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, where Thirteen pence half peny is a Mark, hath set down Forty upon Distress; although the Justices have often offered, that either she or her Friends might redeem the Goods at the Fine. But take his own stating, and the Sum of his Evidence will amount to a clear justification of all those who acted in this matter; for the good Woman being first seduced by the Brotherhood to disobey the Kings Laws, and then to cheat him of his Penalty (which they call passive obedience) by a prudential securing the best of her Goods; the Officers were reduced to take what she her self thought was not worth removing.</p>
            <p>And now we come to another desolation, where the Libeller again cannot see Wood for Trees, not Men for People; and all in the behalf of two beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Teachers (to say no worse) both which had not substance enough to pay one Fine (as the Widow can witness) and by his own calculation also of the number of Hats; which doth not amount to so many as a travelling Furbusher carrieth at his back.</p>
            <p>The next remove is to his Cheats in Parchment, and indeed these deserve to be ingrossed; for here is a Deed maintained to be void of Fraudulency, which was really made and dated three days after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204258:8"/> of the Seller, and the Buyer was frankly told by all the Justices present, as well as Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> that his undertaking for other Mens Debts, over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his own satisfaction, did plainly evidence a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to defraud the King of his Right. But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of the Saints do so much transcend those of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Subjects (they being the first born of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all sorts of Cheats) that their Soveraign Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest (although elder than theirs) must not stand in their way: Witness these new, and their old Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, so that by an inversion of sense they make good the Maxim, <hi>Nullum tempus occurret Regi:</hi> And however this Shark resolves still to play out his hand with false Dice, yet there was not any one person who was pretended to be concerned in the rest of the Debts, did ever offer to the Justices to aver his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest. But some time afterwards the most conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable amongst them, did upon an accidental dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to one of the Justices acknowledge, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there might be some such engagement, yet the Deed was principally framed to secure the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Neither did Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> bind over <hi>Leyfield,</hi> any other ways than by being present whilst another took his Bond, as the other Justices were, who all owned the Act. For the rest of this Paragraph, it consists of speeches raised by the <hi>Libeller,</hi> and falsely impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> but are a most true remonstrance, both of the merits, and designs, of all the <hi>Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to set him right a little, this I have heard Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> will own, that when a <hi>Secluded Alderman</hi> of the most considerable Fortune in <hi>Bedford</hi> did tell
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204258:8"/> him before another Person, that he heard that the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> had said, <hi>They did expect another Day for it,</hi> He replied, <hi>The sooner the better,</hi> if <hi>it must be so:</hi> And considering how nearly related the person that spake it is to the <hi>Basest Transactor</hi> in the Late Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, that ever served any Party; it seems most fit, that the Governors of the Kingdom should determine this Controversie.</p>
            <p>The next Paragraph you will find fill'd with the old <hi>Leaven</hi> and stench of impudent Forgery; for here was no Distress taken when the <hi>Libel</hi> was composed, besides what he himself hath made, upon the Truth and Reputation of some persons, who are of too much Worth and Integrity to have their Actions menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by so Ignominious a Scribler; forthe King'<hi>s Officers</hi> (more out of the Principles of Kindness, than Discretion) did take the words of the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders mentioned, to render their goods when the Justices should demand them; but <hi>Ruffhead,</hi> one chiefly quoted in this part of the <hi>Libel,</hi> did, after a months Indulgence from the <hi>Officer,</hi> refuse to deliver up his goods according to his engagement: this is the <hi>Disciple</hi> of St <hi>Crispin,</hi> who came of himself, and was not brought as in the <hi>Libel</hi> to the <hi>Justice,</hi> and told him, he had refused to let <hi>Feckman</hi> come upon his ground, because not named in the warrant; who candidly let him know (to prevent danger) he could not deny him to enter as an <hi>assistant</hi> to the <hi>Constable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilst we have thus ransackt the <hi>Libellers Cittadel,</hi> he hath gained an opportunity to make his escape out at a <hi>Postern;</hi> the old trick of such <hi>Combatants,</hi> who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204258:9"/> according to the <hi>Scotch Phrase</hi> are bashful before an Enemy: Therefore we must hunt the Purlews to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new the reencounter; and the first intelligence we can get of him, is from a Country Village not far from <hi>Bedford;</hi> where (<hi>guided by his Spirit</hi>) he hath found out another <hi>Canton</hi> of the same <hi>Tribe.</hi> Here he rallies with very much noise, advancing more Colours, Drums and Trumpets, than the remnant of his <hi>Rasca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> than pretend to manage, the Pedant Stratagem to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muse an enemy, whilst he makes his retreat; the first slaunting pelt the Runnagate makes, is against the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of the relation of a little Child, as he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to call her; indeed I do not know by what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he measures the growth of his <hi>Babes of Grace;</hi> but, by the report of the Neighbourhood, she is four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or fifteen years old; and it seems capable enough of <hi>false Doctrine;</hi> for she was an Auditor, but not of the Truth: especially in so difficult a passe to try her understanding, as at the next house amongst her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to know where she was, and whom she saw, which was all the use was made of her: But he makes bold to clip the <hi>Kings evidence,</hi> as well as His <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> for a wife of one of the <hi>Gang</hi> confessed to two others, that she was at the Meeting, and the same day the Constable saw amongst the <hi>Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> an <hi>Itinerant Bawler,</hi> who was Speaker at that Meeting; this and more was informed before any Warrant was issued, which I suppose in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of sober persons will be allowed, is ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a Summons; the Examination and Oath were both taken by several Justices as well as Sir <hi>G. B.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:204258:9"/> as the Warrant under all their Hands and Seals makes appear; but <hi>cui bono</hi> if a single Justice had taken it, as the <hi>Libeller</hi> falsely affirms, the Action was warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; so that all I know can be said to it is, that he gives you this great Lye <hi>gratis,</hi> out of the abundance of his store, but he tells you <hi>that none of them would confess either the Meeting or the Preacher, although they were pressed by the Justices with an engagement to acquit them in case they would do so.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you have him tottering upon his two rotten supporters, <hi>nonsense</hi> and <hi>falshood,</hi> for first, how can a confession procure a discharge, and then the Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces acted more ingeniously a contrary way, for they offered, notwithstanding the accusation, if any could make it appear, or <hi>bona fide</hi> affirm, they were not at the Meeting, they should be acquitted; but the guilt of their Consciences (which never restrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them before) disinabling them to do either, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the confession of the first, it was collected from some others, that they had been there, and so were convicted by the notoriety both of the circumstance and evidence of the Fact, as it now stands recorded; and to convince the Reader there was no mistake in the Justices, after the parties found there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in collusions, the Meeting and the Teacher were openly confessed.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Saint</hi> to be vindicated is as great a <hi>Villain</hi> (with Reverence be it spoken) both for base lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and actions, as the <hi>Libeller</hi> himself, as he was made to understand when he assaulted Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> with provoking and scurrilous speeches, which according
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204258:10"/> to the manners and stile of the <hi>Saints</hi> is suing for favour, and had both <hi>falsely</hi> and <hi>saucily</hi> traduced him to his fellow Justice, and his fellow Justice to him: But it is a shame to publish more of his Character in print, than what hath dropt from the <hi>Libellers</hi> own Pen, even in defence of the <hi>Saint;</hi> for you see he hath like a faithless wretch <hi>broke open the lock</hi> of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other person, who was engaged for his Rent, and <hi>Cancelled a Deed,</hi> which he had passed under his own Hand and Seal, for his Counter security, without either the knowlege or consent of the party; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he mention this Cancelling, until his Son was Convicted, who did after that also acknowledge to the Constable, that he was Owner of the Goods; which appears plain enough by his Agents taking the profit of the Cattle, after his Father-in-laws preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Sale.</p>
            <p>The remainder of this Paragraph, is a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in base Language, that amongst this beggarly Rabble the King must lose his Right; which in truth is his Lot from all the <hi>Conventicles</hi> hitherto Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed: therefore to acquit the Informers, we may upon all accounts whatsoever justly stile the <hi>Libeller, and his crew, the scum of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus against my inclinations, I have been forced to publish the most <hi>illegal, inhumane</hi> and <hi>ungodly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the Libeller and his leaven,</hi> that I might strip Falshood out of the Covering of Truth, and justifie to the World the Magistrates Transactions, which they are willing to submit to the Censure of the Laws, and of all sober People. Neither had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204258:10"/> this <hi>Scribler</hi> the least ground to impute any peculiar or single action to Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> for it appears all along that he hath acted jointly with his Fellow Justices, who (in relation to the Countreys happiness) I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare are so well knowing, unanimous, and active in all parts of their Duty, that they need no Leader; therefore this is easily discovered to be but a stale stratagem of their old <hi>Mareschal de Camp,</hi> or if you had rather of their <hi>grand Muster-Master Satan; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide &amp; impera:</hi> Take off the old Cavaliers first (who can give warning of their Wiles) and then the young ones will become a luscious prey. But to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this, it is not to be questioned, but that our Governours will manifest a most signal kindness and protection to the former, which is the true means to confirm and give encouragement to the latter.</p>
            <p>And now when I hop'd that my task was over, up starts a long-ear'd <hi>Foal</hi> of the <hi>braying Dam,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Calf slinkt by the last <hi>Mate</hi> to the <hi>Geneva Bull,</hi> which some few years since Mooted Wonders from several parts of this Nation, but however it was dropt into the World, I can assure you it stinks like a <hi>Sooterken</hi> after a <hi>Dutch Frows</hi> Delivery, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore presently must be destroyed to preserve the Neighbourhood. Its ill-look'd front bears a scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous comparison, between one <hi>Prior,</hi> and <hi>Feckman;</hi> but as to the former he had never any application to the Justices; except (heretofore) to reclaim his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, neither are any Distresses placed at his house, notwithstanding the Libellers impudent forgery: And as for the Death of the latter, his Wife is depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204258:11"/> that he was seized about eight years since with the like sudden Distemper, to the great hazzard of his life; neither could it be expected that by the strength of Nature, so great a violence should be twice withstood by any constitution. And for his behaviour in the time of his Visitation, to his Wifes, you may have the Oath of Mr. <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> a very Reverend and Learned Divine, whose practice suits (as much as humanity permits) to his Orthodox Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; that during the time of his weakness, his behaviour was sedate, and correspondent to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a dying person, and as for the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had taken from the Justices, he stedfastly declared, that he was satisfied in Conscience that he had done the Church and State good service, as having been instrumental in Executing the Act. And that if he was to begin again he would willingly take upon him the same engagement. Thus this <hi>Libellers</hi> Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as well as his other Relations, are but the fruits of <hi>Sodom;</hi> unexamined, and at a distance, they bear a deluding out-side, but at the approaches of truth, they prove but dust and ashes.</p>
            <p>And here again I would gladly have been acquitted of the <hi>Libeller</hi> and his Crew, having driven them not into their <hi>proper Herd;</hi> amongst <hi>Satan and Witches;</hi> for they also were stiled from the beginning of Times (as old Languages tell us) <hi>Forgers of Miracles;</hi> but this <hi>long-winded Bawler,</hi> hath learn'd of his Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> to turn the other <hi>glass,</hi> for behold a Postscript behind, their Kirk in a Cloak-bag, or rather a great <hi>tayl</hi> fixt by the <hi>Libeller</hi> himself to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204258:11"/>
               <hi>back</hi> of his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> that it may out-mode <hi>Battison;</hi> it hath a praeter-natural discent, from a <hi>Calf</hi> and a <hi>Fox;</hi> for they ever delighted in monstrous productions, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness the Coitions of the <hi>Elders Maid,</hi> and the <hi>Quaker,</hi> with their <hi>four-footed Loves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he uses this <hi>Train</hi> as a <hi>Squirrel</hi> doth hers, to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate and cover all the Cheats and Abuses contained in his <hi>Libel,</hi> which, notwithstanding the small part of the Fox, are easily discerned.</p>
            <p>The first Attempt he makes in this <hi>Postcript</hi> is, with most opprobrious and injurious terms, to state a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel betwixt the proceedings of <hi>Bedfordshire</hi> and those of other Countreys; in which he publishes to the World, that all that have to deal with them must expect dung in the Ballance.</p>
            <p>In the next place, by their old Trayterous Sophism in a new Dress, he maintains, that reviling the <hi>Kings Magistrates;</hi> and reproaching his <hi>Agents,</hi> is no Disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> nor Reflection upon the <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, I am astonish'd to see with what a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligated Impudence he averres themselves peaceable, and their Actions harmless, when the Prince is hardly warm in his Throne, nor his party in the Remnants of their shattered Estates, since by the very same <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> this sort of people did reduce three Nations into one <hi>Aceldama,</hi> and then also, as now, (at the beginning) the people heard the voi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>jacob,</hi> and afterwards felt, both upon thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lives and Fortunes, the rough hands of <hi>Esau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the last place he gives notice of three <hi>plain Ends,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204258:12"/> as he calls them of publishing this Libel; and in this he saith well; for the first is to prepare the whole par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Non-conformists</hi> to be as refractory in their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to the Kings Laws as the <hi>Sectaries</hi> of <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fored;</hi> which he,, in this place, by his <hi>Old Figure,</hi> calls a <hi>patient, quiet and peaceable bearing their provocations and trials;</hi> forgetting, <hi>good man,</hi> that in the beginning of his <hi>Libel,</hi> he hath boasted of their unmalleableness to any Conformity with the prescriptions of this Act, and of the most barbarous usage of the Kings Agents by them and their Accomplices.</p>
            <p>But now for the <hi>Second End;</hi> and the <hi>First End</hi> of that is, humbly to ask our Legislators a nonsensical Question, Whether this be the Garment of their Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring? O the Mystical Metaphors of Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second End</hi> of the <hi>Second</hi> is to return to his Vomit of rayling against the Justices, when they may seek for redress from the Laws of the Nation; but he is too much vers'd in his business to hazard that; for he knows, his Witnesses, like Terriers, will never claw well but under-ground, being alwayes trained up in private Accusations.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third End</hi> of the <hi>Second,</hi> is to perswade our Governours to manifest to the people that they have imposed upon them an <hi>Inconsiderate Act,</hi> by a speedy revising it; but in this I ought to refer him to our <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gislators</hi> themselves to try for an Answer.</p>
            <p>And thus he hath given you <hi>three Ends</hi> in one, to avoid the censure of having no End at all: If you please you may properly call them <hi>a nest of Boxes,</hi> for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204258:12"/> those trinkets are very Emblems both of himself and his <hi>Libel,</hi> as they are filled with emptiness. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though some Criticks may quarrel this Method, yet I can assure them, that this is the old way of branching out Points of Treason and Rebellion to their Vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood; for their inventions are ever swell'd with so great a <hi>Plethory,</hi> upon this Subject, that they never fail to produce superfaetations, often exceeding the <hi>Low Countrey</hi> Ladies Conceptions, more <hi>treasonable Points</hi> than there are days in the year.</p>
            <p>And now (if ever he is to be trusted) he is come to his last End, which is a tazled Repetition of a most <hi>untrue, scandalous</hi> and <hi>formless Babble.</hi> The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject he hath made so bold with, are the Actions of all the <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> in the Nation (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self owns) from the highest to those which act in the most inferiour degrees; that by traducing them to be void of reason, humanity, and righteousness, he might make the same reflections upon the <hi>Laws them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</hi> He also hath made it apparent enough, that he uses the expressions of Peace but to usher in War; for his first admonitions to, and professions of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Peace, and Quietness, are now turned to an Alarm of Suspitions, Heats, Animosities, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions, and Confusions; (to run over no more of his <hi>Rebellious Rosary;</hi>) which, to use his own words, have filled the minds, and do exercise the thoughts of all sorts of Men. And, that he may render a clear testimony of this, he tells you of great numbers of persons who have withdrawn themselves both from their Habitations and Callings, that they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204258:13"/> may not contribute any assistance to the Execution of this Act. A symptom of Rebellion (I confess) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of before, and higher than any of those which preceded the last unnatural War. For, as to the lower sort of people, what other cause can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to leave their Relations and Abodes, than by the instigation of their Leaders to plant themselves conveniently for a <hi>Rendesvouz.</hi> And for those of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quality, I will appeal even to their own Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences (if there is any thing more than the Name of it left) to give their Prince an accompt, why (upon their own accord) they should lay down that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission for the Peace,</hi> which (not long since) they look'd upon as the <hi>most blessed Magna Charta,</hi> to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish them free, both in their Lives and Fortunes, except it be upon the first opportunity to take up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>War;</hi> and if they shall scape unconcern'd, it cannot but be an example hereafter to all faithless persons, upon the least uncertainty of State, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for a change.</p>
            <p>A Wight of this sort was in the Commission for <hi>Bedford,</hi> who employed one that had been a <hi>Rebel in Arms as well as his Worship</hi> (and equally noted with himself for a small parcel of Honesty) <hi>to get the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission transcribed without his Name in the Catalogue,</hi> and in the Transaction his Agent (well vers'd in small Arts) made use of the inadvertency of the Transcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to insert two Gentlemens Names with wrong Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, to disinable them to Act, but the Sum is mispent, and the Commission corrected, yet however there remains a plain Demonstration, that <hi>the old leaven</hi> will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204258:13"/> never fail to play at any sort of Game <hi>to abuse the Government.</hi> Much more might be said to alarm the Magistrates, but by this time I suppose the Reader, as well as my self, is sick of the <hi>Libeller;</hi> therefore I shall conclude with a Request to our Governours, that the Presses may be examined to find out the <hi>Author;</hi> that (according to the Rules of Retaliation) he may be <hi>stigmatized himself for branding Paper.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:204258:14"/>
            <head>The Post-script.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Libel came late to my hands, otherwise this Answer had pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it at the Heels; and if this Lenitive Reply doth not stop the Flux of the</hi> Scribler, <hi>I will publish a more Restrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Impression, with all their Names in the Margin. Pardon me, if to disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse the Nation, I have been longer than I intended.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>